Of the use of artificial intelligence
in our societies
So today
Let's go back to today's discussion and workshop
I'm very much looking forward to do it of course
And I would like now maybe to give the flow to Jean-Yves Iatrides to say a few words
On the side of Air Liquide before moving to the representatives of Japanese embassy
Jean-Yves, the floor is yours
Thank you Sebastian, I hope you can hear me
Good morning, good afternoon, konnichiwa to all of you
So I'm Jean-Yves Iatrides, so I'm located in Japan
And I'm, in charge of the R&D activity for the Air Liquide Group for the Asia region
Thorough that as Sebastian said, it could look a bit strange to see Air Liquide as being part of this event
In fact, first of all, what is Air Liquide for the ones which don't know Air Liquide, or our colleagues in Japan maybe
Air Liquide is a company supplying industrial gases
In fact, we have been in Japan for more than 100 years
So we're not a newcomer in Japan
And of course being part of this exchange program with France and Japan
Is, I would say of use for us
And that's one reason
The second reason is that some hard innovation
As we know the heart of the company, and the company has been created a long time ago by an inventor
Which has been exploring in many fields
And I'm sure at least in some point of his career he's been catching the art also
And now what is very much the focus of the group
Is of course we need to transition
With the development of the hydrogen society
But also looking at any technology
that will allow us to develop a system that build future
And this question of AI is definitely one of the topics
that is very important in out minds
So the topic of the day is definitively
not directly linked between AI and the, we say unusual operation that we have in the company
But we have a feeling that such technology
or such new technology I would say,
which is really disruptive
Addressing, certainly the way we feel, we touch, (and) we get in contact with the things
cannot be only looked at from a short point view, or from a technical (or from) an engineer
I'm a very bad artist I'm an engineer
you know, dealing with numbers, dealing with mechanics, dealing with these kinds of things
But I'm still convinced that when we touch technology, and new technology especially, in the digital world
we have to look at it from a different angle
And this is one of the reasons we have been funding this and this year's program
at the Fondation France-Japon since the beginning of the creation
was to be about to approach topics from a more human science point of view
And honestly (that's uh) I think it's very interesting
it's complementary to what we do
And therefore I'm very delighted to be part of you today,
To listen I would be mostly listening
But again I had the opportunity to meet Eto-san in Paris
a few months ago when I was visiting Paris
And it was really interesting and I think we had a very nice discussion at our research center in Paris
And I think I'm looking forward for the presentation of today
Thank you very much for the invitation
Thank you, thank you very much Jean-Yves for your kind words
So now I would like to, before (the) what you are waiting for and you expected before the talk by Eto-san
I would like to give the floor to Mr. Takenouchi from Japanese embassy in Paris
to say a few words in the name of the Japanese authorities
Thank you for the kind introduction, My name is Yosuke Takenouchi
In charge of science and technology policies at the Embassy of Japan in France
And first of all, on behalf of the embassy,
I would like to congratulate you on the successful organization of today's workshop
As Covid continues to impose restrictions around the world
Science and technology-related events like this are still not as active as before
And under such circumstances I'm such delighted that today's event has come to be held
And I guess it was not an easy task to prepare
So I would express my sincere gratitude especially to Doctor Koichiro Eto
and Fondation France-Japon
and Air Liquide, and all the members involved for their efforts
And looking at the science and technology policies of both countries
In France, a research planning law has been enacted
That sets out the ten year research strategy starting in 2021
And similarly Japan has just formulated the science technology and innovation basic plan
which will run for five years starting in 2021 as well
And the main pillars for both plans are social transformation and strengthening of research capabilities
And education and human resources development
And I see there are so many similarities
In the challenges that Japan and France are facing
And needless to say among the social transformation
Brought about by advanced technologies
The impact of AI is enormous
And this is evident from reading the AI strategies
established in both countries
And discussing how we can make rapid social transformation more acceptable to society
is as important matters as technological development itself
So I understand that the theme of today's workshop is
to pursue the role of art as a solution to this question
which is a very interesting point of view
And I look forward to the presentation and the discussion of the participants today
And finally I would like to conclude my greetings
with a wish that today's workshop will be an opportunity
for our new collaborations across research fields and borders
Thank you very much
Thank you very much for your kind words Mr Takenouchi
And now it's time to give the flow to our colleague and friend Eto-san
so we hope you will enjoy this workshop
and enjoy the discussion as well
so the floor is yours, Ito-san, (in Japanese) douzo
Oh thank you very much. My name is Kouichiro Eto
And first, I would like to say thank you to all participants
Especially both speakers and audience
So I would like to start my presentation without further moment
Okay, I would like to start my presentation
My title of the presentation is "Art brings the future to our society"
And I am a 2021 FFJ/Air Liquide Fellow at Fondation France-Japon
And also I am a researcher at AIST
First of all, I would like to thank everyone who helped me make this workshop possible
First I would like to thank Mr, Jean-Yves Iatrides
from Air-Liquid corporation
and professor Sebastien Lechevalier from Fondation France-Japon
who made this fellowship possible
Thank you very much!
And I would like also to thank to my colleagues at FFJ
Fabien-san and Itoh-san, Jodie-san, and my colleague in Japan
Thank you for all
Before getting into the main topic
Let me explain the differences from the original plan
The initial plan was to investigate the cognitive differences in AI between Japan and the West,
However, it turned out to be difficult due to the reasons shown here
Therefore I have shifted the plan
I have defined the final objective
to investigate the relationship between AI and advanced technology in Europe
I appreciate your understandings
First, let me introduce myself
I have been working as an artist since the 90s
Then in 2002, I joined AIST and started working as a researcher
I would like to introduce two of my works
they are in common that they are works that they make the internet visible
This work is "Web Hopper"
You can see a world map on the screen
On this map you can see the user's web hopping trajectory
For example, let's say you are looking at a website in the US
Then you click a link to a Europe one
Then virtually you have jumped from the US to Europe
By analyzing internet traffic in real time
I could visualize the trajectory of web browsing
we published this work in 1996
we won the grand prix of Prix Ars Electronica
At that time, the work became a permanent exhibit
At the arts Ars Electronica center
We won the grand prix of Press Electronica
the press prize is the most prestigious award in this field
this exhibit is a hands-on model of the internet
This work shows how internet works
You can see a white table in front of you
And this is a terminal
Here you can make a packet with black and white balls
the first 8 balls are for an address
and the last eight balls are for data
You can only send one character at a time
Then press the "send" button
The packet goes through the internet
And the router moves the packet from the local area network to another network
So this is a routing table
And then a packet go from the (terminal) out to the internet
Then this is the destination terminal
The packet goes to the display of the terminal
Then the packet go into the display
You can see the content of the packet
which is a character "A"
We created this work in 2001
and you can still see it in the museum in Miraikan
If you have a chance to visit Tokyo
please drop by Miraikan!
What I would like to explain here is a period in the 90s
This age was a very early stage of the internet
At that time, the internet was an advanced technology
These works explain how the internet works
for the general public
Since 2002, I have been a researcher at AIST
continuing a research theme, how we can design a press for co-creation
The key concept of my research is that the users should design the system
This picture is of a famous architect Christopher Alexander
He said that the users should design the architecture
If we do that, we won't need architects anymore
Instead, he created a pattern language
to make this concept possible
a method to design architecture without architects
this idea is a key concept of my research
We created several co-creation platforms
that connects various fields based on this concept
The most significant achievement was the Niconico-Gakkai beta
We created a platform that connects the general public with professional researchers
Even if they are not working as professional researchers
there are still people doing research
We call them "Wild Researchers"
And we created a press for them to present their research with us
We started this project in 2011, and held 9 large scale symposiums
The first symposium attracted 110,000 audience on the internet
The total number of viewers was over 658,000 (615,000?) people
Since then I have expanded my activities as follows
I would like to share the latest research result of our research
In January of this year, we published this paper to classify
74 facial emojis on the valence-arousal axes
Pleasantness and intensity
We published this paper in Scientific Reports, and it is press released from Nature Asia
And now I would like to start explaining this fellowship result
First, I set the research question as "What is the role of art in advanced technology?"
then I would like to move onto the background, method and findings
First, there are already some pioneering studies on the relationship between AI and art
First of all, there is a book "AI for creation" by professor Nao Tokui from Keio University
He is also a speaker at this workshop
His book is a very detailed description of
how can we use AI to develop human creativity
Also, professor Sofian Audry's book
"Art in the age of machine learning"
is published last year
Go back to the history of the computer art
This research is also excellent
Also the MDPI journal "Arts as a special institute" on "The Machine as Artist" in 2019
which includes 17 people's 17 papers
all of which are very worthwhile
And let's start with an explanation of observations in Europe
I visited various events and centers where arts and science are related
Ars Electronica is the most significant example in Europe
This center began as a Media Art Festival in 1979
the oldest and biggest in the world
They started Prix Ars Electronica in 1987
the award is the most highly regarded in the media-art field
In 1996, they opened the Ars Electronica center as shown in this picture
And they also started an R&D center
called "Future Lab" in the same building
But my relationship with Ars Electronica is strong
I recieved the Prix Ars Electronica three times
Including the Grand Prix of 1997
From my point of view, the most significant result of future lab is Spaxels
They started the project in 2012
to draw pictures in the sky using drones
They named this project "Spaxels"
The meaning is "pixels in space"
I saw the initial launch event at Linz in 2012
In honest, I felt that the light was so weak and unreliable at that time
But this project grew steadily
In 2015, they started a joint research with Intel
And they developed this project far away
In 2021, Intel drew a symbol mark of Tokyo 2020
At the opening ceremony of Tokyo (Olympics)
And they held the Ars Electronica festival in 2021 again
but it was a hybrid event
Usually the festival attracts so many artists from all over the world
But this year, there was almost no artists from overseas
It was a quiet event
But I found an excellent exhibit
Future Lab also produces exhibits for the Ars Electronica Center
In this video you can see 11 monitors in front of you
In these monitors you can see the hidden layers of DNN
As you know, there are many layers behind the deep neural network
And this exhibit shows the mechanism of the DNN very well
In detail, they use the CNN (Convolutional Neural Network) with the VGG16 network
I think this is a simple idea but effective
By showing the layers all at once, we can see how the DNN works
I had a chance to interview Hideaki Ogawa, the co-director of the Future Lab
I was impressed by his words,
Just as water comes out when you twist the tap
The future comes out when you type "twist the tap" at the Ars Electronica Center
He is also an artist still creating their artworks
Events like this Ars Electronica are now taking place in other cities
In Paris, there is a similar event called the Némo Biennale
They held the event at Centquatre and various other locations in Paris
They designed this event to connect science and art
I participated in this event and I felt that the direction was so close to the Ars Electronica Festival
And there are events called Maker Faire
where people who like to make things gather and show their creations
The maker faire events are all over the world, and the Nantes Maker Campus was outstanding quality
And also, I am a director of Tsukuba Mini Maker faire
Then I met several artists and interviewed them
First let me introduce "La Machine"
The moving giant elephant of Nantes
In the city of Nantes, big elephant carried a lot of people around the city everyday
And I had a chance to interview the artistic director Mr. Francois Delaroziere
And according to him, it is important to have such huge artwork moving around the public open city and open space
And I felt that this is loved by the citizens very much
From Francois Delaroziere
I was particularly interested in his focus on movement
And according to him, movement is a language (of) a machine, and a mechanical organisms
The next artist is Scott Eaton
The picture on the left is a finished painting
The video on the right side shows how he is drawing it
As you can see, it is just a simple sketch with an outline
But the AI automatically drew the content with human body
Scott Eaton has a background in art
and he also graduated from the MIT media lab
so he is very good at computer science
And he studied drawing and sculpture in Florence in Italy
I think his paintings are under the influence of Michelangelo
I had the opportunity to interview him, and it was fascinating
I think he has a great philosophy as an artist who uses AI
In particular I would like to emphasize the word
"For an artist, failure is sometimes beautiful"
I think this is a natural appeal of media art
Creating art through repeated experimentations
Next up is Fernado Magalhães
As you can see, he created a computer graphics image
that looks like Japanese superheroes
He didn't make these images by hand
But he designed an algorithm to create superheroes
Based on that algorithm the program generates countless superhero's shapes automatically
This kind of art is what we call "Generative Art"
I interviewed him also
He was born in São Paulo Brazil
and watched Japanese TV programs in childhood
So it was there that he came in contact with Japanese culture
and begin to create these kinds of works
So I would like to explain what I have learned from these experiences
First of all I would like to say that I have (never) been to more places
One that most impressed me was Grotte Chauvet
This Grotte Chauvet is a cave mural that exists about 36 thousand years old
Lascaux cave is 20 thousand years old
So this is probably the oldest cave mural
We see here a replica of Grotte Chauvet called Grotte Chauvet 2
Although it is a replica it is so realistic
It looks like (the) real thing is here
Here is a mural of lions, but it exists within the same reality
I was very impressed by this
And before I came to France, I thought that this "Europe" was a place where the modern western culture has developed
But that was not the case
I mean the coast of Mediterranean sea is where civilization begun
I was finally able to understand this
Then what force drives the progress of civilization?
The science fiction novelist Neal Stephenson invented the term "Metaverse"
in his novel Snow Crash
In this book, he says that there are some layers of languages
And the civilization progress is through the power of crossing between these layers
In his word, "Code" or programming language, is a latest language layer
A language defines our thinking
It is difficult to share a concept that has not yet been put into words
Please imagine this:
How would you tell yourself in 2019 what was the changes brought by Covid-19
I think you will find it a bit difficult
Once a common language is established, sharing concepts becomes possible
And the role of human in a society is dictated by the measure of technological changes
The industrial revolution was governed by natural laws
In particular, how to control engines was very important
Locomotive automobiles, looms, and letter presses are all powered by engines
Please remember that the term "engineering" comes from engine
On the other hand, the IT revolution is governed by language
So when we can express it in a language, we can execute it
For example, we often compare a hacker to a wizard
When a wizard casts a spell, it becomes true
In this situation, "the spell" means a programming language
And next, let's consider the AI revolution that is taking place
I believe that AI is governed by imagination
In AI, everything exists in a probabilistic way
There is not rigid distinction between 0 or 1
From my point of view, this is closer to painting than language
I mean, In other words, what can be visualized can be executed
I remind Scott Eaton's statement that "The artist controls the AI with his imagination and ideas" is a perfect example of this
So I would like to return to the research question
What is the role of art in advanced technology
My findings are to be a source of imaginations
and expands the possibilities to advance the technology
So I would like to end my presentation
And thank you very much
Then
Can I go progress?
Yes please, I will give you the floor to organize the round table thank you very much!
There will be
I think there will be many questions
And congratulations of course though on your talk
But I think in order to have a good discussion it's good to move to the round table
and then to have the discussion
Okay thank you very much
Then let's start the session one
So in session one we have a presentation from *Attos* first
Then we will have a presentation from Nao Tokui from Keio University
Tokui-sensei, could you please start your presentation?
Hi, yes, thank you!
(in Japanese) Kikoemasuka? Do you hear me?
Uh yes, clearly!
Thank you very much
Okay so, hi everyone
Bonjour, thank you for having me
So let me start my presentation
So can I share my screen?
Normally, you can share, you have the right to share that
yes
Okay, thanks!
So today I will talk about AI and creativity
And before that let me introduce myself
So my name is Nao Tokui
I'm an artist and researcher
And also I'm a founder and CEO of Tokyo based art collective Qosmo
And I also organized
computational creativity laboratory at Keio University in Japan
So today, I want to talk about
AI and creativity
And Especially the main theme of my talk is this:
Is AI capable of creating something new and original?
Maybe more precisely: Is AI capable of helping us create something new and original
rather than imitating what we humans have already created
So why I got interested in this topic
Is this,
I entered the University of Tokyo in 1995
And joined the laboratory, I mean the AI laboratory in 1998
And also at the same time, I started DJ'ing myself
And I got kind of obsessed with music
And I started thinking like "I want to create music, I want to create new music nobody ever listened to"
so
But I don't play any musical instruments
and I don't barely read musical scores
so how can I make interesting music
so naturally I turned to programming and AI
So here, I'm not interested in optimizing and streamlining the music making process
to make more hit songs more economically
Rather, instead, I'm interested in
diversification and deviation
so how can I make something unique music,
you know basically a new music
And here I have an agenda of my talk today
So I want to talk about three topics
And first one is "Misusable" AI tools
The importance of music tools you can misuse
And you may find it a little bit strange to use the word "misuse" in the discussion of AI
But when you look back the history of music and other creative fields
you may realize that it is in fact a history of misuse and misappropriated new technologies
So one of the recurring patterns is when an artist use new technologies in a way the original inventor didn't intend or imagine
It is when new form of expression emerge
So the prime example of these misused technology is for example
turn table and samplers
So as for turn tables, you are not supposed to touch and move the vinyl record right?
And samplers were invented to imitate expensive physical instruments such as pianos and violins
But the inventor didn't expect users to appropriate and sample somebody else's records and musics
Such as Funky Drummers or Aiming Brakes or whatever
And when we think about the current status of AI music tools
or AI creative tools in general
You see both extreme ends of spectrum here
On one hand, you have programmer oriented tools
like, so you need to install Python and Tensor Flow and you need CUDA of course
And you know, you need to get used to these tools to make something unique or something new
And I'm sure some artists can learn and train themselves to get used to these tools
but usually it's not the case
And at the other end of the spectrum, we have
very well-packaged tools, AI tools
So with one click you can generate a music or with one click the AI can edit your photo, or images, you know
And in some cases, that's good
But I think if the tool is too well packaged
then you cannot "misuse" or you cannot use these tools in your own way, or in your own creative way
So I think we need something in between these two ends of the spectrum
And I call it "Misusable" AI tools
And following this principal, I created a simple AI tool for musicians
And it is on Ableton Live, a famous digital audio workstation software
And yeah, so this is an Ableton Live plugin
And what it does is it allows you as artist to train your own AI model
within this software, so you don't have to deal with Python and CUDA
So only thing you need to do is just collect music data, in this case MIDI files
and drag and drop on this device
And voila, you got a trained model on this device, and you can generate new rhythms continuously
And you can:
♫sick beats♫
I hope you can hear the audio
And a good thing about this tool is that you can actually "misuse" this tool
So you can train your model with very obscure data sets
or, I don't know, this device is meant for rhythm generation, but you can train your own model with a melody data, for example
and see what comes out
Okay, that's one small project I did in 2020
And I want to talk about the second topic here
Which is embracing the uncertainty or errors AI brings
So this is a visualization of the output of the same model I just introduced
And this is useful and great, and also you can misuse this tools to generate something unique
But still you need your own training data to train this model
And mainly you can say like this model is still imitating human creation with AI, right?
So in 2017 I created something called "Neural Beatbox"
So what I did is to combine rhythm generation model, the same rhythm generation model,
with a sound classification model
And you can play this neural beatbox on this website neuralbeatbox.net
so if you're interested please take a look
what I did was to integrate the sound classification model with the rhythm generation model
And generated rhythm pattern will be played
with the instant drum kit
the sound classification model created out of the recorded sound materials
♫beatbox♫
So we created this website during the Covid lockdown
on this website you create your own beat with the help of AI and you can share your sessions with your friends
So that you can join your instant beatbox session
And I should mention that sound classification is not perfect of course
but that's what we wanted
We wanted to deviate from what humans have created
♫sick session♫
Okay ,so what I just said is like this
so when you try to create something new and unique you want to deviate and branch out from the conventions or common senses
And we hope it will be a manifestation of creativity, but sometimes,
Especially from a conventional perspective, these deviation can be just a mistake or an error, right?
So we need to know how to embrace the mistakes
And you have to know how to differentiate mistakes from, you know, a manifestation of creativity
And this error and creativity is one of my main theme I think
So the other project where I embrace the uncertainty of AI is this AI DJ project
It's a back-to-back DJ session with me
and AI DJ
and AI DJ selects and plays sometimes unexpected songs
But this uncertainty leads to very interesting DJ performance
So sometimes the AI selects something I didn't expect or I couldn't imagine
But this unexpectedness was so interesting as a DJ
And we are so fortunate to have opportunities to play at various locations including Google I/O in San Francisco
and Scopitone festival in Nantes
So we extended this scene and we turned it into a real-time AI jam session
♫sick jam session♫
I hope you can listen to and hear the audio now
(In Japanese) Daijoubukana?
Anyway, so instead of letting AI to select existing music
We made an AI system that makes music on stage in real time
So in this performance, three AI models, namely
rhythm generation model, baseline generation, and loop selection interact with each other
And keep improvising a dance track
So I as a DJ intervene the processor by manipulating mixer and adding a sound in the turn table
So it's not a disk jockey anymore, it's more like a machine jockey or an AI jockey
Okay, so finally I want to talk about this, pushing AI to the edge
And so let's get back to the original question: Is AI capable of creating something new and original
So here I want to talk about Generative Adversarial Network
So it's a famous framework so I'm not going to explain it in detail
But it's so famous for the capability of generating very realistic faces
But here, I want to use it for, again rhythm patterns
And in this model I added a conditioning input
so you can specify the genre, and generate patterns
*silence*
do you hear the audio? I cannot hear
Uh I cannot hear
somehow
Good? No?
No
*deafening silence*
Sorry, do it again
*drum plays for a second*
Okay
*silence*
So again, I added a conditional input so that you can specify the genre of the generated rhythm patterns
But it's not interesting, so I added another discriminator to this model
I added another discriminator that is for classifying the genre of the generated rhythms
So the generator is trained to confuse the additional discriminator as well
so that it can generate realistic rhythm patterns that don't belong to any genres in the training data set
So this is the result
*sick beat ensues*
I hope you can hear, I don't I can hear (Yes we can, and it's awesome!)
(In Japanese) Daijoobudesuka?
*sick hit-hat beats*
So here, I wanted to realize the tag of war between conventions and deviations
So now AI is trying to tell which deviation is good and interesting
And this is I believe what human artists do actually
And finally I want to introduce one of my favorite quotes of Scott Adams
He's a famous comic writer of Dilbert comic strip
And it goes like this: Creativity is allowing yourself to make mistakes. Art is knowing which ones to keep
And in the context of AI and creativity I think AI is a tool that helps you make interesting, meaningful, and amusing mistakes
And consequently, it helps you to create something new and original
Okay, finally as Eto-san introduced, I published this book last year
And I'm working on English translation, and hopefully I can deliver it within a few months
Okay, so thank you so much!
Thank you very much Tokui-sensei, I loved the presentation very much
I'm sorry about the audio trouble
No no, no problem, I have so much questions for Professor Tokui
But on this program, I will do the presentation for session one and all
Then we'll have a 10 minutes Q and A
So I would like to do this and to next presenter
So next presenter from IRCAM Professor Gerard Assayag
Assayag-sensei, can you hear me?
Yes, yes.
Okay, thank you very much for accepting the offer to be a speaker of this lecture.
Could you please start your presentation as I can say?
Okay.
Here you are.
Can you see it?
Yes.
Perfect all right so,
My presentation will be about my ERC European Research Council advanced grant REACH:
Raising co-creativity in Cyber-Human Musicianship
First of all let me present IRCAM,
the place where I am a researcher
So IRCAM is the institute where we research the coordination of acoustic music,
which is actually a part of Centre Georges Pompidou in Paris.
It was created by famous conductor and composer Pierre Boulez in the 70s when the when the Centre Pompidou was created.
And it is the the music and sound research parts of Centre Pompidou.
So we have a three part in IRCAM,
a research lab called Science and Technology of Sound and Music (STMS),
who is operated by CNRS and Sorbonne University and IRCAM of course, and the Minister of the Culture Communication.
We have a music creation department
with concert halls and composers in residence.
And music commissions etc.
And we have an education department where we have a master's program
first for young scientists,
and another program in technology for musicians.
So it's a very original model of innovation and creativity
where we have artists that are immersed into a research context.
All right, so in IRCAM I have created a team called Music Representation team years ago,
and now it has become the biggest team in IRCAM.
And we have a lot of researchers on AI and creativity for artistic purposes
specifically music.
So we have five poles in this team,
so certain of these poles are concerned with
music, composition formalization, and formal approaches to music.
But we have the three poles here are really concerned with artificial intelligence.
So REACH is really the project that I will be speaking about.
ACIDS is a project that is highly oriented towards the machine learning for creative applications.
And activities is really oriented towards the idea of time, and how you write and control the time in an interactive setup.
So to give an example, here is a program that I wrote many years ago,
and has now become the standard all over the world for a computer-assisted composition.
It's called open music,
and we have published three books where
thousands of composers explain how they would use open music to create new music.
So open music is actually a programming language but it is a visual programming language.
So composers learn how to program more easily because it's totally visual and they can design new musical application.
So this is not the artificial intelligence approach, this is the formal approaches,
where composers actually have to specify the algorithm that they want to use in order to create music.
After having created open music with of course with my team,
I have moved to the idea of creating intelligent interaction with agents.
With creative agents so we are moving closer to artificial intelligence.
And again quite a number of years ago, I created with colleagues
the OMax paradigm of intelligent interaction.
So you see OMax is really the simple idea that you have intelligent agent
feed with AI that are able to listen to music either in offline or in real time,
that are able simultaneously to learn.
So apply a machine learning model create a model, so a mirror of musical memory,
simultaneously scan and navigate the memory in order to generate new materials
and propose this new materials to the musician.
And then you have reaction,
reactions on both sides, the musician will react to the AI, the AI will react to the musician.
And we have this creative loop.
So OMax had a lot of hairs and descendants,
and you see many popular systems that have been derived from or original researches
on the OMax paradigm.
And notably all the work that is done right now at Sony Music and now at Spotify is
(and also the) work done by François Pachet,
was immediately derived from our original research work at OMax.
So OMax has become a very important paradigm,
and we have moved from this paradigm to something even more interesting right now.
But let me just give you an idea of what this interaction paradigm is about.
So before learning, the system must listen.
So you must have a perception aware system of listening.
We call this machine or artificial listening,
so that we're gonna we're gonna segment the stream of music into
musical in it that will be distributed over some mathematical structure or maybe a geometry,
and we will discover with cognitive algorithm a symbolic alphabet structure.
Even though we are dealing with audio, we will discover a symbolic alphabet structure of on the musical unit
that will deliver a symbolic stream.
So from the symbolic stream we will learn a model.
So we will use a number of machine learning algorithm
and then regenerate and render new sequences.
And the three processes listen, learn, and generate, are real time and concurrent
and they are both concurrent and cooperative.
So the nice drawing that you see here is the visual representation of a musical sequence
that has been learned in real time by OMax.
And all the colored arcs that you see are actually connecting different places of the music with regard to similarity.
So because we have this connection created by the AI,
we have a kind of cartography of a map of the music.
And the system just have to navigate around this map to create new sequences that will be statistically coherent with the material that was learned,
but still creative and novel.
So you see here in this model you have the musician who is for instance improvising,
and there is a double loop.
He's listening to other musicians and but he's also, he or she, listening to to themselves,
and also listening to its sound memories.
So himself or herself in the past.
And the memory is a virtual part because it is constituted by all that the musician has played,
all that the other musicians are playing,
and all that the musician has ever played or learned in his life. So this is all virtual.
And this is exactly the musical memory that the AI system is simulating.
I'm hearing some music coming from somewhere.
Okay, okay okay.
Okay, so somax is like you know, this zero point here in this graph that represent two dimensions
where you have the reactive dimension the system reacts instantly to a musician.
and the planning dimension where the the user can actually plan behaviors like compose for instance
a harmonic grid or any composition
so OMax is really at zero because it is not really planning
and it is not reactive but it has a lot of machine learning
so then we have we have developed more intelligent systems, like a smart system
where we have a high level of reactivity
we have developed the important system where we have a high level of planning
and now we are working
on a hybrid system where we would have a good compromise
between being totally reactive to what the live musicians are doing
and also having some planning and being able to develop interesting
and sophisticated and structured musical processes
so here is the the general diagram the that we are now exploring in the REACH project
where you have some musical input musical signal
you have a machine listening unit that creates a symbolic signal stream
you have a learning unit that will do some machine learning, statistical, probabilistic, or deep learning
that will learn a model and that will give back some information
to the listening machine
so it will help the listening machine to improve itself
so the learning will create a memory model
where we will have an interaction agent
that will query the model in order to create new musical material
but that will still be listening to the
musical stream in the input
so the interacting agent will be able also to be reactive and not
only creative and generative
and the user will be able to specify scenarios so to compose some
music
but then the interacting model will be able to give feedback control to the scenario unit
in order to be able to generate artificial scenarios that will be interacting with the user in general
so this is a highly sophisticated architecture that will be able to generate very interesting
musical experiments
so now let me show you just two-minute video
where you will see some example or where we have reached so far
you will see a pianist playing
and at some point you will hear three singers edit *piaf elizabeth schwarzkopf*
and *b holidays* who are very famous singers
so we have used audio archives
but the AI which will totally re-improvise the audio archives
in order to align the improvisation with what the pianist is doing
♫Pianist playing♫
♫The AI starts improvising in real time♫
♫Epic collaboration between the pianist and the AI♫
oh sorry
♫Brief playback♫
♫Epic human-AI jam♫
okay so you have seen two examples
one was an offline example where the AI has learned a lot of materials from the three singers
and then is able to recompose and re-improvise in the audio domain
but as well also in the video domain the music
and in the last part of the video you have seen a real time example
where the system captures and learned his model in real time
from what the musician
is actually performing
and is able to instantly interact and have a dialogue with the
musician
so every time you were listening to the saxophone sound
and the musician was obviously not playing his instrument
it was the AI playing and proposing a dialogue to the to the musician
okay recently we have begun a national research agency project called MERCI
Mixed Musical Reality with Creative Insturments
where we have an industrial partner called HyVibe
and HyVibe has obtained a lot of awards in the industrial
world
for instance there is the challenge award of the best startup for 2021
and they are designing a active acoustic system
that where they transform material devices into an acoustic diffusion system
and they have created they have
created a new instrument called the HyVibe guitar
that is equipped with actuators and sensors and computing power inside the guitar
and where you can, you can have some processing of the sound of the guitar
that is rendered not by a loudspeaker but by the wooden body of
the guitar itself
so it gives the the musician the feeling that the instrument is really reacting to what he's doing
so here's an example
♫Creative guitar performance♫
and another
so so what we want to do is to be able to embed the artificial intelligence into the instrument
so this instrument is not only capable of extending the sound of the instrumentist
but also to add an intelligent musical layer to what the musician is
doing
and maybe to co-improvise with the musician
and this is what we call co-creativity
when we have an interactive situation where a musician and a computer system are able to co-create or co-improvise
and this is where we get to the
REACH project that has just begun the last year
where we are kind of wrapping up and summing up all this big experience
in writing AI system for interactive music creation
where we want to really really focus on what I call co-creativity
between human and AI
emphasizing that creativity is an emerging dynamics resulting from
complex interaction between actors
so it cannot be understood by considering each
agent's production in separation
but on the contrary you have to consider really the sum of the behaviors of the agents
so this frees us from the concept of artificial creativity art artificial intelligence in the art
because creativity is not a state that
you are trying to reach
it's a dynamical effect,
an emergent effect of interaction in a complex system
so you can never catch really what creativity or co-creativity is in a static way
it will only emerge in the time of interaction
this is the idea that we defined in REACH
so cyber-human co-creativity will appear when you have emergence of
cohesive or contrasting joint behaviors
that you are not able to reduce to individual processes
and then you will have operation of non-linear regime of event and structure formation
that will create core evolutions of forms
and this happens because you have cross-learning processes
where the machine learns in real time from the musician
but the musician learns in real time from the machine
or in general agents that can be artificial or human
learn from one another in a cross way
and this will create complex
feedback loops and reinforcement mechanism
that will favor the emergent mechanism
So a cyber physical system like the guitar for
instance is a cyber physical system
they create an interaction continuity between digital and
physical world
now we want to propose the term cyber audience for systems that create a synergy
between the digital models and the human mind the human creativity
so this is the the structure
of REACH
but mainly what we have is two central tasks
that are kind of converging one to the other
one is to augment the digital agent's abilities with better AI algorithms
enhance creativity autonomy sensitivity to context
but also cyber physical extension like the guitar
so they can act in the material world
on the other side we will take the human and get it closer to
the digital agent
by augmenting the human ability by interfacing them into embedded mixed realities
so for instance the the creative guitar that we are doing with HyVibe
is our first mixed reality instrument
so something that augments the the natural reality by a digital augmentation
so the REACH artistic impact is huge
recently we had the concert at the *maison de la jolla* music with
the *orchest national the jazz*
and they were playing with our algorithm that were interacting in
real time with the whole orchestra
which is more than 20 musicians
we have issued a new record and a book called "Artist This Year"
where you can listen to all this interactive concert with AI,
and you have 200 pages of critical analysis and commentary of the
phenomenon of AI in art.
A lot of concerts festivals etc where all systems are actually
used in real life
and I will just show a one minute video where you will see the same
kind of human augmentation
but here is the video so we use the archive of Dianne Reeves' concert
at the Monterey Jazz Festival
and the archives is controlled by the AI in order
that it's able to
react in real time to what the pianist is doing
♫The singer AI is reacting to the pianist♫
so thank you for your
attention and I will stop here
Thank you very much Assayag-sensei
your presentation is very interesting and deepful (deeply insightful), thank you very much
and I failed to tell this earlier for our audience
if you have any questions please post questions to the chat
We will have Q&A later in this session
Then next, I would like to welcome Professor Jean-Pierre Merlet from INRIA
Merlet-sensei, could you please start your presentation?
Okay do you hear me?
okay I think you are
seeing my screen right?
uh I I'm sorry uh you have to monitor
yeah that's a problem
Ah, okay, let me see
Can you share the window on the left side
wait a minute I will activate the second screen
maybe you can share
not for a monitor for only a window
oh
do you see my screen?
no
no? not yet
no you don't see anything?
and it's coming and maybe we
can wait for a few seconds and I think it's going to be fine
sorry for that, I will disconnect my second screen
I don't know what is happening
zoom is not really working well for me
of course you can (you are) okay to share a full monitor, then I think you can
Yeah but
is that okay with you do you see my screen now?
did you see my screen?
No, I don't think so
No?
I don't know what is going on
I propose maybe you can send
me your your presentation and I will
But yeah I have videos so
Oh you have videos
I don't understand, stop sharing?
and I'm really sorry because I have to update
my zoom and the new one is not working
application windows okay maybe I can try
that one and here do you see my screen?
hello?
no no no, I mean it's black
it's black yes
yeah only black
it's black? but it's written you started to share your screen
yeah I think I have a problem with my display system
I don't know
Um...
I don't know what is happening
so you don't see anything?
We don't see anything
I understand you are sharing your screen but we don't see anything
arriving on the screen actually
Okay, let's try again
Urg, I don't understand
you could hear the monitor for the first time
so yeah I, this is what I'm doing
do you see something?
no
an hear?
so you don't see my monitor at all right?
no
I'm sorry about that
I don't see
I don't understand this usually
should work except for this problem of
maybe you can reconnect your
(your last) your second screen and
this is what I have done
okay
but you don't see,
Jean-Pierre?
you don't see anything
Oui?
what if you, sorry hello everybody, what if you send your slides via file sender?
But the problem is that I
File sender? to download and...
yeah but the problem is that i
have movies.
Ah you have too many yeah okay, sorry
okay but I will, maybe I can, I don't
know why you don't see the screen
you can change the order of a presentation
for example you can switch Magali-san and Merlet-san
then we have some..
yeah but this this will not
solve the just sharing problem we have
let me try something, you don't see anything at all right now?
A black screen or something like that?
just a black screen
black screen
okay so I'm sorry I don't know what
I can do there
okay I can send for sure I can't send the presentation but this could be
a pity because there are a lot of movies going on
maybe I will, okay you can
switch I will try to reconnect and
maybe just try to disconnect and reconnect maybe
I can try that
yeah but
new share, let's try new share
let's try something else
you still don't see anything
no
right
and I'm really sorry about
that I don't know what to do
this usually works except for this actually appears this morning
so maybe yes we can
close the zoom program, the zoom application then connect to zoom
okay I will do that I will
disconnect and reconnect again
so maybe I don't know if someone has a question
maybe we can take one question
yeah it's better to use this time to hold Q&A so if
anyone has a question to audience (from audience)
Of course if you have question to Professor Tokui and Professor Asayag, and ask them also
yes, I have a question for Mr. Tokui
how did you create a GAN (Generative Adversarial Network) for this?
because I think it's very difficult to create a discriminator for what is a right rhythm and wrong rhythm?
Or Marlet-san, could you please share?
(In Japanese) Oh, kitakitakita.
Marlet-san ok
it's very good
(In Japanese) Are? Kikoeta?
Marlet-san could you please say something
I can see your sharing monitor,
and sharing window, but I cannot hear your voice
(In Japanese) Are? Nanka,
(In Japanese) Hmm, Doushiyokkana
Fabien-san how can we do?
yeah I'm looking forward
very strange
(In Japanese) A, Kita
okay do you see my screen now?
Yes I can see
okay so I will
go fast to, sorry for some delay
so I'm Jean-Pierre Merlet
I'm working as a robotician so I'm not an artist at all
I'm working in a team which is called HEPHAISTOS
which is working basically on providing assisted device for frail people
um
probably that
I don't see my screen so I cannot go up and down
okay
so what are the benefits for
scientists to work with athletes
this is the question I have to raise
what are
the benefits for artists to work with scientists
those opposite and our other application
domains may benefit from such a collaboration
it's difficult to work with artists for a
scientist
and I assume that it's difficult for artists to work with scientists
because
there are a lot of problems
so what are the benefits for scientists?
Well, you know in our research institution
it's not really expected and sometimes
it's even seen as quite suspect
Furthermore, from an evaluation from a scientist evaluation
viewpoint
it's difficult to evaluate because we don't have indicators
and collaboration with
artists requires a huge understanding effort
what are the benefits for artists to work with
scientists?
well a major difficulty is that
the scientist is some kind of in between
between the artists and the work
most of them are
many of the artists are not aware of technological
possibilities
so they have an attitude of self-censorship that limits the creativity
and
they're also the understanding effort for our people
they have also to understand
scientists
do you still hear me?
I'm not sure because I have absolutely
no sound
no that's, yeah? it's okay
So let's go to to a practical example to show
you that
in spite of these drawbacks we have
the possibility
and it's a very interesting
possibility to collaborate with artists
I will illustrate site on this example where we
have a robot
which is called the cable driven parallel robot
and the purpose of this robot is
to be able to move the point b that you see on the drawing
the platform with this guy underside
moves
his platform in all direction x y z
so we can raise the platform go to left go backwards and upward
and to do that, we have four cables
which
are attached to the platform
and are also attached on the winch at point a
and the winch allowed to change the cable lengths
and by an appropriate control of the cable length
we can change the position of the platform at will
oops
there is an application of this kind of robot
in the earth's domain
which is assistance to mobility for frail people
for example where we're
making transfer operation
helping them to go for example to go to a sitting from a sitting
position to a standing position
and also for working assistance
with the benefits of providing
autonomy they are able to do something that
before they were not able to do alone
which
improves self-esteem (and) improved social relationship
and it's also very interesting for doctors
for monitoring the health of the subject
because this platform is instrumented to give
medical information
so let's just show me (let me show you) a short video
if it works
I hope you can see
the video
you see a patient on the bed
the robot is coming down
the patient is in
a medical harness
and I'm losing the job but basically the passion can do it alone
the robot will lift the passion to move her
in a wheelchair
so she will be now again
fully autonomous
I will stop the video
but already this robot has this kind of having inclusion of art
so for example maybe you know the pink singer
and this is one of her
public performance
she moves over the crowd using this cable powered robot
and you can see
she will do something very french
at the point I don't see the video on the screen
you don't see the video?
no video
not this one not the previous one as
well
pdf
I'm sorry but okay
this is probably the same issue with my screen
i
will skip that for the sake of time
in 2018 we have a magic encounter with
an artist whose name is Anne-Valérie Gasc
during a workshop devoted to the use of robot in
architecture
and Anne-Valérie was looking for a machine
with the purpose of 3d printing a
structure on large scale (with) dozens of metals
the printing material is glass microbeads
the machine has to follow a fixed trajectory
and deposit layers of glass powder
but there is no gluing element in the product so that the
structure slowly collapse after each layer
and an exhibition of this structure
was scheduled for the summer of 2019
in an art center located close to paris
we get interested in this project
because we have made a huge effort on the theoretical modeling and control of
this kind of robot
we are interested in long-term deployment because this allowed to test the
robustness of our system
and especially to detect failure understanding why something
has failed
and detecting unexpected behaviors
the objectives we have was basically increasing
the safety and performance of the system
for dealing with uh our assistance problem
so you see a picture of the exhibition place it was huge
the length was about 40
meter so it's about 20 meter 25 meter
you see there's a drum that is moved by the robot
I will not show the video it's it's
basically bad but I cannot do anything to get that
also maybe I try maybe let me
try something
I hope I will not lose
maybe you switch the video now
Do you see the video?
ok, I can see
I don't hear you
I can see the video
okay, all right
So, (unintelligible noise)
and now it's deploying the powder on the structure
okay we'll stop the video move back to the
talk
I hope you see the the slide now
so some result of this exhibition
the exhibition
lasts for one month and a half
the robot traveled for more than four kilometers
walking in
average four hours and fifteen minutes per day
76 layers of glass powder were deposited
which represents 1.5 tons of glass
and we have some failures
one cable
breakdown during the installation
and two small failure encoder on one axis
model
but so was it was not really important
next we move to ICRA 2020
the same exhibition was scheduled to be part of a big
robotics conference
which is, whose name is ICRA
which have 5000
plus participants in Paris during June 2020
we have improved the system but unfortunately
ICRA was postponed because of the Covid
and our new exhibition will take place during the
summer of this year in a museum close to to this
lesson learned
from art to science
we have
received a huge benefit in taking part of the exhibition
from a scientific viewpoint we are a
single team in a world which is able to master a very difficult issue in this kind of robots
furthermore this experiment they offer
unique test bed for researchers
working on dune information
dunes formation modeling
but still many of the
colleagues, our research colleagues, indicates that
more or less valley
yeah
could
you please (move) back to the pdf?
back to?
we see the stopped video so
could you please back to pdf?
okay um...
let me see
okay
now you sh...
okay you skip my slide
so I'm backing up lesson learned
from a scientific viewpoint this
experiment was very interesting
but still many of our research colleagues state
more or less overly that this is not real science
it's also said that the government's
level of the interdisciplinarity is
very good is a necessity
but in the practice
of such official speech is quite different
because the evaluation committee are not
very comfortable with such a collaboration
what we need also is that discussion with doctors and artists have a lot of similarity
they have a different language (and) they have a different
level of scientific knowledge
but for us it's quite uh interesting because this exhibition
has facilitated our communication with doctors
now lesson learned from science to
art
many artists believes that that animating an artwork is a complex and
expensive task
this is no more true, even for motion except for very large artwork
To illustrate that in 2015 we have organized
a workshop
called computer science for art
which results
so it was a five day workshop
which
resulted in a concept at the end of the workshop
with the device developed by the artist during
the workshop
and I can show you a picture of this concept
you see some strange machines that
were making musics
both on the ground on the table
you see a dancer
for example the dancer as an
accelerometer on her hand
so that the music was changing according to a motion
so I moved to conclusion
and sorry for the delay
for a scientist wondering on domains quite different from our
main research field is very fruitful
this allows us to develop new algorithms new software newer
methodologies
and all this work may be used for other research topics
in our case working with
artists has allowed us to improve our medical device
facilitate our discussion with doctors
but also to better understand human acceptation of the device
which is quite essential
for us
and to better understand the patients needs
so this will end my presentation, and sorry for
the technical problem
thank you for your attention
thank you very much for an excellent demonstration
I understand this conclusion very much
so
this time this is the end of a session one, and from now uh we'd like to have some Q&A
session
so if any and anyone has a question for the speakers
could you please raise your
hand or say something from my microphone?
hello
Please, Assayag-sensei
You have any question? no?
maybe you started a question
uh quick you know maybe
yes I have so many questions
Assayag-sensei, I'm very interested by your presentation
I think IRCAM is very good to improve and advance the possibility of music
so I'm very impressed by your work
how can I say
the guitar with a vibration
so how what is the
initial motivation of, to create this kind of guitar?
okay so uh as I said
one of the
fundamentals of the REACH project
is to state that creativity shared with the machine
can only be an emergent process
that will appear in the course of interaction
and so that you cannot really describe what is creativity for a machine
and maybe this doesn't have even meaning
but you can describe creative or
co-creative processes that are emerging
because you have a complex interaction
between agents
artificial or humans who are related by a cross-learning
phenomenon
so once we have moved into this realm
we have realized that in
order to really have this convergence between
cyber augmentation which is augmenting the
the the capacities of various algorithms
and human augmentation which is augmenting
the capacities of human towards the algorithm
we needed, we really needed a physical step
that is a step where there would be some embodiment of the human
into the process of interacting with
the machine
so the guitar is only the first try that we make
the first step of of trying to
to to create the condition for such a physical embodiment of the human
by embedding the algorithm
into a physical device that the human really has against his body and feels like an extension
of the of his body
but it is just the first experiment of course
we would like to design many
other instruments or any kind of devices
where this emergence of co-creativity between human and
machines
will be really the result not only of an intellectual process
but of a physical embodiment
of the human
and maybe sometimes because we we had a robotics presentation just before
and maybe also a physical embodiment of artificial creators too
thank you very much I'm very
impressed by your idea of co-creativity with machine
and then I have one question to Mr. Tokui
and I already
asked the question
so could you please answer it?
so how I train my GAN model
on rhythm, that was question correct?
okay so maybe I was not so clear about my project
so the first step was uh to train a normal GAN model
a Generative Adversarial Network model on
rhythm data
so it's I think relatively easy for you know GAN's network to capture the the essence of rhythm pattern
But I thought it's just
another imitation of human creativity in a way
that's why as a second step I added another discriminator to the original GAN framework
then the second discriminator is not is not expected to classify
training data from artificial data
but it's expected
to classify the genre of music generated
so the original discriminator
was trained to classify
the real data from the fake one right?
that's the core concept of the Generative Adversarial Network
then I added a second discriminator which
does the classification of musical genres
so the origin generator
was uh uh trained to confuse not only the original discriminator
but also the second genre
classification discriminator
so I expect
at the end generator will be able to generate
something that sounds like a realism pattern
but these are patterns that
don't belong to any genres
So you created a triangle of discriminators combining them
I understand a little bit
Okay, Thank you very much
the original idea was, when you think about artists
maybe think about any famous artist, picasso for example
so he started to, you know, train himself to capture the...
Sorry, let me rephrase again
so picasso, or any other artist should start painting to imitate somebody
else's style right?
so I want to be like this artist or that artist
But Picasso or any other artist at some point they start trying to deviate from the existing styles
so there is some kind of, like how I can say,
the conflict between
like staying in the existing style
and also, like deviating from the existing style
so there is very delicate balance between these two directions
so I wanted to make
realize that conflict within the GAN framework
yeah I understand okay.
you mean that all artists have uh their own discriminator in (of) their own
The one is to imitate another
artist
and another discriminator is to escape from the uh traditional art
so i understand that it's very interesting and it works
very well
Thank you very much for your presentation
Merlet-san, can you hear me? I have a question for your presentation
And I understand that you are a scientist and
uh have collaborated with us artists
So is there any point, the important point
to successful collaboration
with artists?
what is the point
Ah, yeah
this is, we have to adopt a very different mind when working with artists
compared to other work we may do with companies
and stuff like that
for two reasons
because they have the, main for many reasons in fact
they have a different language, and we have a different language
so we have to understand
each other sometimes we use the same word but with different meaning
so that we need to create
some kind of dictionary between the two community
then the artists are not always aware of all
of our technological and scientific constraints
well what is really make me
afraid (what makes me afraid) some time is that
when an artist tell me oh I have just a minor
detail to change the system
the last time they the artists tell us because we work with many
different artists but the one we are working with right now
the last time she tell me that
results in 400 hours of work changing everything
But it's okay
at the same time we really
learn from the way people are seeing our work
the view of the artist is very different from
the view we have
and it's very close to what the passion tells
so it's very important to have this
discussion with us
because it's opened our mind
Okay, thank you very much wonderful episode
And thank you for all and then we'd like to have some uh...
Tokui-sensei, can you read the chat screen?
Magali-san has a question to Tokui-sensei
sharing the same point of view uh which are the
ownership
Ah, I see and this is not question I think
then I'd like to have a coffee break for now
and we can see the screen of a video from *arya material*
and you can see the
video from (that) I took in this state in Europe
Look through the video with a cup of coffee and sandwich
*A video interview of a french person*
five years ago I saw some small demonstrations
of it doing like really expressive remapping
from like gesture drawing to something somewhat
photographic I thought that that was
an amazing way to encapsulate knowledge of the figure is
in a neural network
I can see a lot of the same challenges that the neural network will try to
understand
that an artist tries to understand
the artist controls it from his imagination and
his ideas and then he kind of confers the routine
that's what I discovered that I was able to do
with the AI at a University I did arts
but engineering was my primary degree
my work is somewhat of the understanding from
engineering and then my artistic study as well
and so a lot of my photography
initially was to support
my my own understanding but
also the anatomy lectures
and that's usually how the the project starts
with kind of a concept that I visualize in my imagination
and then I try to see if
it fits within the techniques that I've
explored whether it was possible
I guess one
of the reasons why maybe my stuff is different
I try really ridiculous ideas just to see how
interestingly they fail that part of the process
is maybe a scientist or a researcher but even as
an artist the failure is sometimes beautiful
I understand the boundaries of what machine learning
can do and then just test it and see what happens
*Another video is playing back*
from Japan uh his name is Akira
just approached the idea of creating characters
because he worked for me was like really
mind-blowing I decided to uh to find my way
as well
I'm trying to convince myself to finish
so what I want to do is like a massive
project I would say like 10 000 different creatures
the tools allow
me to work on at this scale and I want to try to see what comes out of it
*Another video is playing back*
okay uh thank you very much
so I'd like to restart the session
from now we'd like to start session two
after the first presentator is professor
Lionel Obadia from University of Lyon 2.
Obadia-sensei, thank you very
much for attending this symposium
could you please start your presentation
I'm trying you hear me
yes I can hear you
all right fine I don't have videos and I hope
everything will feel right for my presentation
and I'm really happy and to be there thanks
for the invitation
I see that there are a couple of people that I know around the table
but it is
another story
so I share my presentation right now
and
I can see
can you see it?
yes
all right let's
go for it
I'm just trying to have this um
uh well well well, I'm sharing but I want to have
this
okay I'm going like that
okay do you see just one one slide?
okay perfect
okay great
this is a very long title and a very short reflection that you will see
and I'm a social
and cultural anthropology specialized in religion
Asian religion to be a clear
and I've recently, since a couple of years (ago),
I'm converting myself to the steganological study of
digital technologies
and robotics and and so on
so just one point if I have a problem for the presentation
since I do not see, all right, I do not see my screen
yeah, and, so a couple of
reflections starting from fieldwork that I've been conducting season since one two years ago
I tried
to submit an ERC (European Research Council) advanced (grant) but uh unfortunately, they,
contrary to other colleagues around the table
it was not successful this time that it will be resubmitted this year
but digital magic and I'm
quite glad to hear that professor Merlet talk about magic in the context of robotics
this is exactly what I'm trying to explore now
And so I will talk about today, humans and the the tendency and the and the trends in robotics
and in world society to consider
that
robots and all these kind of 3d AI forms have to be human shaped
and what kind of cultural
imagination it brings at the forefront of the agenda of a
reflection of technology and culture,
technology and society, and technology and history
so we all know that the digital revolution impacts
coming in there in a wide range of form and effect (in) now
we all agree that we live in
a networked connected world and society
and interaction with these devices, small ones (and) big ones
have become natural and natural means in our lexicon (to be) culturally accepted
So we are, many now studying these new attitudes representation and cultural frameworks and imagination
that give means to technology as they infused society and daily lives
and there is this kind
of interaction in between technologies and culture and society complete
and ongoing uh feedback in between the two
my anthropological point of view
it's culturally focused, (and) it's comparative
and I'm conducting ethnography of labs, exhibitions, enterprises, university everywhere
where I can find people that are trying to design, develop, test, use, and socially distribute these very strange devices
called AI robots.
so I'm in the second month (as a) professor of anthropology at the University of Lyon
but I'm in the second month right now, in two labs.
The first one is (in french) Centre d'Internet de Sociétés, Center for the Study of Internet and Society
so this is all about communication device and the sharing information and so on
and I'm also associated member of the Institut des Systèmes Intelligents et de la Robotique
Institute for Intelligent System and Robotics
where I'm conducting my field work among other places
where I'm doing this field works
and my paper will emphasize images and belief through attitudes, cultural expression, (and cultural expression) at large including artistic one
but I will
not talk about arts in this presentation today
this focus on robots especially robots, rather than AI and other digital device
this focus is mainly due to the fact that robots
indeed raise the crucial issue of human shape form of technological creations
so this paper is not on art except that I'm participating on an ongoing research
with people that were are working on art
this is a seminar titled robots on stage interdisciplinary conversions between robotic and theater
this is a network and people are working together
you can see an image of what they do
they are studying plays and robots in place and AI in plays (what the heck is he saying here???)
and this is one of the *place* that I've been studying and presented in this network
but my focus will be on arts let's say popular arts
the movies, literature and online
So these robots, AI and other so-called creators
as seen from the side of social sciences and humanities
means not users but designers to users on the human side
and the empirical studies demonstrate that we have the evidence that AI is everywhere
but still it is nowhere because sometimes with the lack of materiality and the previous papers
underscore this point that we have to materialize and that,
Eto-san, your own paper to put emphasis on the materialization and visualization
of these devices and software
so it depends on the perception of their silence and materiality
and the same for the degree of reality of the integration of this device in our life
unless I left beside the issue of cultural difference
in between France and Japan, and France and the United states and so on
and countries with a lower economic development for instance
where the issue of this technology is an issue of cultural framework by which this technology are understood
is raised in a quite different way
but we'll talk about culture and society in general because of the very fast generalization
then this is important to take into account that
there are the inequal social and cultural distribution of device
and their availabilities, skills, and knowledge
and I heard several times this morning
the issue
of failures the issue of not understanding the issue of something wrong in the behavior of the machines
and still this is really important to understand
or as well what humans provide as meanings
and especially when it's about non-rational meanings.
again these robots AI software and algorithm and so on are distributed on a different scale
they are very small one that is hidden for instance
in a smartphone application
and other ones that take the shape of a big robot that you can face you can have a face-to-face interaction
then one thing is striking is the fact that
not most not all but a significant
part of these devices are shaped against
the human face or human shape or
human body shape
and it raised the question of
are we trying to make new humans or are they still (making) machines
and it raised the outcomes of the issue of mimesis in between
humans and machine on both sides for instance
besides the issue that social sciences and humanities are trying to raise and trying to explore
is the interaction in between these humans and devices
and the correspondence in between human to human social relationship and human device relationships
and in reality only in imagination
and this is a war scenario for science fiction movies
machines to machine communication against human
that you know that this is really dystopic
and a quite widespread scenario of robots against humans this is one of the most used
let's say a background by which we imagine uh the the future in movies
especially in famous north Americans (famous in north America)
so we have different side, different forms of materiality from flat devices
screen that are everywhere on 3d devices
robots for instance
and 3d that can be real
if you see a machine acting that's why it's on (what) the professor Merlet has demonstrated
but also, you can see also 3d device
this is a 3d representation
but what's new as an anthropologist I'm interested in the fact that they are continuities and rupture
in the relationships in between humans and material environment through techniques
and I'm quite fond of this theory that
imagine that there is kind of a ongoing relationship
to materiality and to things that we shape
so humans seems to have always been
interested in mediating their relationship to reality
thanks to technology at large
start with very very primitive technologies
and it end up in hyper modern and quick massive wave of all these devices
that are colonizing our life
robots conversational agent algorithm software
robots connected objects and so on
for many different purposes
domestic, military, education, artistic purpose for instance
or some AI generated arts or AI as an inspiration for artists as a
representation
then we live in this new ecosystem of so-called "anthropology significant other" are mediated at
so the anthropological outlook on this
is that if we raise issues regarding our relationship
to AI technological device and robots for instance
there are already topics like ethics and trust,
something that has been already treated and discussed by psychology, philosophy, and law
but SSH (Social Sciences and Humanities) can bring like a lot of dimension taste and proof
from the appeal to robots and AI
and belief in these devices are animating by something
and then anthropology, sorry for uh insisting on this point,
but want to highlight how humans are in practice creative with machine
and how also they inject imagination futuristic scenario and even present scenario
and how the scenario infused society
and my interest raised in the fact that this scenario also impacts different
sectors society
including technological ones means that the people that are building these
technologies
are actors like *OOO* and actors and they are influenced
from the best or for the worst influenced by this imaginary frames
and then I will focus on image and imagination through these screens and visual culture
but let's start for the beginning and these new mechanics, automatic robots
are located according to the frame of imagination at the frontiers between
humanity and the rationality between fiction and realism
and especially human with robots that capture maybe most, maybe more than even all the other ones
this kind of imagination
and then there is an interesting discussion in robotics right now
the tracing back to meteorological routes
this is a widespread tendency and there are two trends that
if you as an anthropologist read literature in robotics, not very technical, but more open to history and culture
and you see that there are sub-community of roboticians that think that
AI and robots are in rupture with ancient forms
means that it used to be some kind of representation
and either human shaped things, quasi human for instance,
TALOS that you see that has been built by *ephrais* and the *feistos* have already been mentioned today
not the program but the the ancient Greek code
and other ones that think that AI and robots are only the continuity of an ongoing mythological (and) mental scheme in the human brain
and these continuity can be seen as well in what is called now the animistic design of new technologies
and the idea that there is something inside
something that is haunting the technology something like a soul or something (adeptus mechanicus?)
that does it above or beyond um the rationality and the purely mechanic
life of things
and this even turns to a modern religious robot I take two examples here
and one in China and one in the west
these are robot priest and in some context, even the religious system clearly accept the presence of robots
but as vehicles of belief
and one thing is really important is that we are witnessing something really really different now
it's a belief in robots and they believe in AI as religious schemes or as a religious object
and to mention the rise of the thanks to,
because of Levandowski who used to be a an engineer at Google
the first church of AI that considered that AI is a godlike create
but these robots, and I focus here only on robots,
it comes under a vast array of types and prototypes
you can have small parts of the body and you can have the full human humanoid body
and this is thanks to, also a clear and quick advance in personal robotics and biomimetics,
sensor elaboration, algorithm-inspired emotions, and and so on
that makes some of the uh organizations and enterprises creating robots
attempting to create robots more and more resembling to human bodies
and if you allow me a slogan, because anthropologists like to produce slogan,
Are we shifting from bios, the system setup, to bios life within these robots
and this is a kind of witnessing or revealing unveiling this obsession for anthropomorphism
and one thing is surprising, striking, is even the representation of AI as a software (on) the flat device
is anthropomorphized as you can see on the on the on the small picture on the right
because of intelligence and intelligence it's supposed to be in the brain
but there are also other theories about intelligence
anyway,
all this brings us to the idea that we start from and end up in the representation of human body.
and then these new programs in human centered AI and robotics tend to respond or seem to respond
to this human tendency to consider technology as a replication of living real hard actions.
But these humans are flat or 3d, almost human or meta human and so on,
range among very different forms
and only the adjective seems to validate
and you keep the human substantive noon and you take a lot of, they inspire a lot of adjectives (like humans, almost humans, and meta-humans),
depending on what you mean and there are at least three epistemological regimes that you can raise after this adjective
for instance, they said like humans almost humans are meta-humans,
if you consider that these humans resemble humans only if they are almost human
that they tend to be human that they will be one day, as human or just like human,
and the meta humans is they are supposed to be evolved humans
and in my research, I'm conducting a interesting experience (experiment),
in which I ask people to react in faith in front of all these meta humans for instance
you see that on my screen this is on the left but on your screen it may be on the right
this is this they are quite handsome lady this but this person does not exist because it's an AI generated face
and also there are these double humans for instance
this character of Star Wars that was in Star Wars one and died in the meantime and was recreated through AI techniques to incarnate a new character in recent uh star wars movie even if he's dead but he has the same face he has the same movement and of course he has the same voice and the digital human experience it's also interesting because it's a conversation conversational agent with face attitudes so you feel like you are talking with
something that is almost human not really human it's in between and creating a very very strange
different ways to being human race of course a series of questions and I'm trying to
frame them after different questions and different theoretical patterns to to
put concept on them first the issue that has been raised previously or as well the
acceptance of these virtual humans we I'm talking in front of people from Japan
so *mori's* famous uncanny valley is still a concept that will still discuss but was just
a very specific step in the perception and interaction with a very specific type of of
machine and robot but the uncanny valley has been widespread in the meantime and now this is a huge
concept that we can manipulate and redefine in order to understand what what's the thrill that
you have when you meet these non-humans but they are also human they are in between and
this is the open door to understanding the very magical thinking that is in between
humans and mesh so these devices assume different forms they are co-operative functional therapeutic
friendly assistive and so on and they create a vast array of emotion as well but these emotions
are mixed together they create anxiety fear for instance people are really afraid of robots thanks
are due to science fiction movies or literature but also because they are across the road of of
of robots and but this is not always the case most of the of the time the people have fun with
robots and there and to a certain extent and a very specific context they also feel
empathy and love and sense of security but I'm talking about this therapeutic robot's name *paul*
which is made for all people with a psychiatric psychological trouble and then they are
something that is coming in between what I call the three t but this isn't that time and if it
doesn't work please tell me and please create a space for discussion in order to contradict these
these these atoms to theorize the human to robots relationships the tools of this robot
are first tools but they are also toys we are playing with these devices and coming back to
this in in a second and they are also conditions I mean temptation because we create something more
than a relationship we get also emotions and we are committed to this device for instance
this kind of obsession with this device up to sexual desires because now we are
witnessing the rise of sexual robots and not only in Asian countries but also in Europe and north
America and then I think that and this may be also a certain way to get closer to the artistic milieu
thinking about play play in three different terms of three different definitions of the terms
first is playing with reality we are in a game and there is something happening that we know
this is not exactly reality but we are trying to play with reality and the second is to play
in a non-real but real context I mean playing like you are a character in a theater then you
knew you know that you are doing something that seems real but it's not real that's like a game
but now you are playing like a character and all this brings us to play as fun because people
enjoy doing this thing they enjoy they are they have a lot of positive emotion and they are also
counterbalanced by negative emotions at that time but these emotions this effervescence against
robots and the relationship with robots give rise to really interesting scenarios from the
science fiction and there are four examples of robots that are purely autonomous imaginative
they are driven by emotions even if they are not supposed to have emotion for instance in the
the lady on the right is a robot named *arisa* in a series that you can find on Netflix better than us
and she ends up in sacrificing herself to prevent the life of the family and she is
in love with the dad of the family but there as you can see also *yule bruner* just before is
is a pure emotionless robot he's killing people in the first movie in the 70s of of
Westworld but he's driven by anger so he shows no emotion but he's killing people because
he wants to he wants revenge against the human all this is developed in the realm of scenario in
the real imagination and so on but on the field when I'm studying for instance in the easier
this this robot that you can see on the on the left the so-called *baxter* robot in which their
motion trying to trying to make this motion more sophisticated and the two examples taken
from an exhibition in which they are collaborative robots small ones that are supposed to be vacuum
cleaner robots collaborative with each other and the famous paper which is welcoming people at the
start the at the door of the exhibition and then we get back to a crude reality and
one of the researchers in robotics told me we are quite far from terminator and around three
and then why there are so different narrative and you know that we know we all know that
technologies are embedded in nets of meaning and to enter it in this narrative but do these
autonomous devices need narrative and of what kind and I allow myself the the chance to divide this
narrative in between scientific narrative and fiction narrative even if they mix each other
the distinction between the the two of them is just purely theoretical but scientific narratives
tell history of technology and fiction narrative that history about about technology and leave room
to very strange things that are coming up to be reality right now for instance imagining that
there are robots everywhere like in the drawings helping children helping elder people and bringing
parcels to homes and so on and making love with a robot find something that you can imagine but
these two images are also counterbalanced by the fact that we already have uh
virtual girlfriends in Japan and so this wasn't essay and and the papers in
helping for elder people in their homes so we are not quite far from scientific and
fiction narrative in the reality that we are living but the most interesting is not that
okay we can explore and explore and explore these fictional narratives but these narratives end up
being storytelling for robotics organizations and enterprises first there are a lot of people
are telling us that this is the story this is a theological narrative we are going
towards the inescapable origin of robots in society and that's almost human in society and
there are two famous enterprises that use a lot of media technologies such as YouTube to produce
different videos Hanson Robotics and Boston Dynamics they are very famous and the first one is
created Sofia. This human shape robot face which is able to have a conversation with the humans
and these are very famous very sports robots that are keen to accomplish very very difficult
motions and these are very spectacular performance and they are broadcast intentionally by these
enterprises and this is fascinating for the wide audience and a lot of people discussing this as
oh this is the future robots you see that women robots and these these very strong and even
military robots and but this is upsetting for the robotician I'm working with
they said okay this is just spectacular things but this is not the reality of robotics
as it is developing right now but interestingly these same atoms to
broadcast the the performance of robotics brings about dystopian scenario and this is all
except for the killer robot down in the slide but the two ones the robots is fighting back
Boston Dynamics roadways is fighting back against human and Sofia from Hanson Robotics telling
okay I will destroy humans these are fake fake videos but this means that the kind of genius
side of the of the coin when you try to broadcast an utopian future and said okay we live with
this very very powerful performance and very powerful robots and immediately they are also
contrary visions and contrary imaginations and then it brings me I'm almost finished to the what
i call the cultural walls in digital revolution because my approach is also a sociological one
I'm trying to understand position discourse and framework of imagination and the way they are
intentions and from this field work I'm framed for *ideative* attitudes to AI and robots especially
robots in this case what I call technologies that means engineers and technicians that are
elaborating robots and most of them told me that okay this is all but spectacular screen and this
is a software and we are trying to frame algorithm and then to see to test the movement and the part
of the law and so on and this is quite long and quite rigorous way of of doing things and on
the other side they are what I call technologies don't leave guys that come on TV and write books
and say okay the future of the digital age will be robots everywhere sometimes they are the same
Elon Musk for instance is a pure technology and these prophets of the digital age
and describe the future as a full of these devices may be it for critic critics be it for kind of
*valorization* of this also there are technophilians developers and users that are fascinated by these
new technologies and technophobians okay four positions but the surprise come by the fact that
we are not only and not really in a face-to-face confrontation with you on the one side those
who believe in the future of robots and robotics and say okay there are technologies we live robots
will be like gods like new angels like new spirits of the time and the other side technologies that
bring this back to the crude reality and saying that this is not exactly that this
we have to be rationalists this is all all but all that reality and more most of the time we find in
the scientific literature this kind of tension between rationality and irrationality but it's
much more complex than that because first I give two examples technologies for instance can
be technophobians and in my field work I met some people that create robots but fear the development
of AI in the same time these are the same people and this is the complexity of human feelings and
human attitudes and for instance on the other way technophilians people that like this
technology are not always always technologies and most of the user in your ignore the process on and
the design of creating technologies and finally technologies can inspire but not always and annoy
but also inspire technologies for instance we know that in France they are they have been not in
France not only but elsewhere invitation from the government and the organization and invitation
for scientists and authors to imagine matching and scenario for the for the future so it's not only
coming from the technological mid and slide and I'm finished and sometimes technologist
meets technology and there is at least one enterprise in France I'm doing field work with who
level their products enchanted tools and I set up even a marvel section because when they create AI
and robots they know that they are designed with their own history and the imaginary framework they
sell you the robots and the cultural and symbolic universe of the robot they all come together
and like Alice in Wonderland in the same time you cannot have without the others and
this kind of reconciliation in between fiction and science fiction between imagination and technology
then this is thanks to imagination robots then there are more much more in the line of
social exception acceptation and and this enterprise is supposed to be on the technologist
really rationalist regional side leave room for imagination and help this creative
relationship with robots and a.m and blur the frontiers and give party ground for imagination
I come from the east side of the of the creators of rob and at final reflection just a sum up of
these points this is all again an ongoing research and these are some results but not all the results
this paper was just to reflect upon the issues of sciences I determined to a digital revolution
and a very specific object in digital revolution especially robots and the anthropological point
of view that has been adopted here was from the bottom from the actor's point of view
and how and why and who produce what kind of technological imagination or imagination
projected on technologies and these human shape devices that are present here today are a good
example but are not the only one and all have been said now I might be counter balanced and
critically converted to other devices and other conditions of producting and using these
technologies of course these are technologies are also source of different kind of images and
surrounded by a different framework of imagination but my conclusion is creative imagination is not
always where we think it is and the appropriation of these devices in the media of artistic media
is a key evidence of this point but my look was on the technological media and the and widening
communities of roboticians and this imaginary cultural imaginary then can nurture or prevent
the advance of and in technologies I mean and this is my final conclusion we always from side to
side from the beginning of thinking about robots a and digital technology and producing them and
distributing disseminating them in in societies and culture think about the the very crucial role
of imagination it means images and ideologies surrounding these technologies thank you
thank you very much professor Obadia for wonderful presentation and i
love this kind of topics so I have so many issues to this I'd like to discuss with you
but the first I'd like to start the two three more presentation for this session
then I'd like to discuss all with us so the next I'd like to welcome miss Biin Shen from China
she's an artist and she's a great artist and I'm honored to be welcome(ing) here Biin Shen
could you please start your presentation? sure thanks Eto-san for the introduction
so today I'm going to share some of the experience I developed after I returned to China
so it's great to be here and so I'm sharing the screen now can you see it can you see it
sorry let me just, yeah so I will ask my avatar to do this presentation for me today
okay who okay
yes I can hear you no doubt that technology has played an increasingly important role
since the 20th century humans have to face multiple crisis and dilemmas
from nature society and humans themselves. In such a closely interconnected world can the collisions
of different cultures and ideas inspire creations that helps technology develop the better solutions
hello everyone my name is *Vincent* thanks to Dr. *either* for the invitation it's my great
pleasure to be here with other professionals at this workshop
I'm interested in the relationship between humans and technology to be more specific
I'm interested in how humans perceive or understand technology in a different culture
I have studied at m8 design interactions with professor *raby* at the London Royal
College of Arts that's also why a part of my work includes speculative future scenarios
technology has been around since the dawn of humanity from stones for hunting to sticks to join
all of which are the products of technology in human society in this time although
technology is presented similarly in general due to the globalization nowadays since I moved back
I have found a common phenomenon in China
people have a pretty different view of technology than what I haven't seen in other countries
there is a park at center of beijing called
temple of heaven which seems to have become a testing ground for local creativity of
innovation even the toilet in this park have equipped it with face recognition technology
going to the loo in his park must not be an overly urgent task like in no times you can
only get the pieces of toilet paper after taking off your head and your glasses and staring at the
machine for three seconds the slowly dripped toilet paper is limited each time so if you
need more you may have to repeat the progress a few times before go into the toilet oh and
you can also get the toilet paper from the front looking of pikachu I have texted through my phone
there are many more cases here from a noodles performance robot
to a piano that can grill lamp kebabs to the Shenzhen's smartphones Chinese citizens
have unique optimistic altitudes on technology these attitudes re-establishments how they live
in their living environment which also influenced my art creations
the ancient Chinese cosmology there's a set of thoughts and rules behind the seemingly magical
talisman it is a virtual miss blended with reality such as rim making ceremony and at the same time
is the most sensory reflection of how people at each time have understood their natural
environment resembles the way how algorithms and data shapes are meant *fulu* is a thousand *talisman*
that uses writing a meditation spell and spiritual power to scare away evil spirits attract fortune
or perceived peace in the space they are hung up or paced onto *fulu* is a drawing consisting
of Chinese characters with a mythological origin more than writing that merely describes the word
these characters have a magical relationship with them that allows them to act upon reality nowadays
the word of network's *timo lecra* gradually adopts and even replaces reality benefit *tissue's*
narrative of data becomes resources or even capsule the emergence of blockchain technology
and its decentralized worldview make it possible for internet nomads to build a better life
and these fictions are often regarded as objective depictions of reality
the character "Shu" in old Chinese means method skill extending from the meaning of the past
"Shu" also expressed both technology and the witchcraft which presents fiction there are also
cases of fictional transformations of reality in the records of dynasty in the novel heroes
of wood marine may eventually their depictions of diced monks and rivers who armed solely with diced
tools and witchcraft were able to overcome the machines and bring liberation for exploited people
continuing with this fiction or ancient wish of the Qing Dynasty I have created a speculative work
a series of contemporary fools for the society that is entirely overtaken by technology
this attempts to help people break the current human dilemma that both by the technology
and to explore the value of fictional realities
in this work I invited Hong Kong calligrapher *quinzo* to invent
some food together to harness the invisible magnetism of algorithms in combination with
ancient beliefs for example the image on the screen is for bitcoin holders it can
convert any electronic devices into a bitcoin mining machine for attracting more bitcoins
we decided to let this alternative future so so now you can get those flu online
technology
new techniques a type of liberation and autonomy or just enough
use in space be liberated or trapped
in his book
only
thoughts have succeeded in tips but
also helped general products not all Asian
essentially in the exact nature like this
hmm
peace on
is is it disconnected
hello b sound are you here hello okay I think I saw some icons appear on my laptop said
connection is not good can you hear me now can you hear me now yes yes
okay so I will start sharing again okay okay can I say it yes okay cool
you
to allow the public to encounter their world anew a German noise assignment transported 1999
used smartphones on trolley surreal streets of Berlin and google maps recognized this activity
by turning a green street red and automatically producing a virtual traffic jam on the map
the fictional activity also affected the physical world where smart navigation
directed cars to alternative routes to avoid being stuck in this traffic this is not racket
poses potentially to generate fictions often take as accurate attentions of reality another example
is Sunday island image at the right side was featured by google earth through their satellites
imagery and market in the contemporary digital charts such as google maps from 1876 until October
2012 when scientists finally discovered that the island have never existed the marina favor is a
network commissioned by unesco creative cities to critique the relationship between humans and
technology as game is one of the common mechanism used in my creative practice I have built a
telephone game with the artificial intelligence program tits translated in his work the text
is translated between 10 rooted and distant language families to decipher the original text
after the text has been translated and re-translated the original meaning is lost and the
cyber formatted linguistic endpoints is obtained the project results from negotiating questions
such as chameleon be accurately represented in translation from human accessibility to machine
logic what does it say about us trusting the perfection of computers over the sentimentally
of humans using these questions as a foundation running human or philosophical
text through a programmatic data obscures the language mechanically the resulting text
visual images its final step relieves on the intuitive and imprecise thinking
that mirrors human perception english writer and creative
we only see what we look at to look is an act of choice I think art is particularly important
in this area than ever as everything in its reality is attached to capsule
by reviving the power of fiction art change the real world in the current technological context
to generate awareness for technology for work citizens to rethink their current states
to catalysts for the better futures and that's my talk today thank you very much
oh wow oh thank you very much your presentation is also an art hard work
very beautiful thank you very much yeah yeah thank you very much
i have many questions to you but I'd like to proceed to the next presentation
then and let's discuss so I'd like to welcome mangaly and martin mozarix from inaliya
so could you please start your presentation yes I'm sharing my screen thank you
and that's
oops so
is it working yes it is indeed so thank you again for inviting us and my name is Magali and
in the name of INRIA, CNRS, and *lucia* and Terra Numerica we would like to to thank you
you Dr. Koichiro Eto-san for this invite and also the french and Japanese foundation and early kid
i'm sorry but our presentation is going to be very different because it's to share the
project we are working on at the moment in help maritime in the south of France sophia antipolis
and thank you to all of you for your excellent and exciting presentation and
i'm still very very impressed by being shane as well and it's going to be hard
to talk after her so Terra Numerica is digital sciences at your fingertips it's
something like we would like people to discover explore and experiment
so why Terra Numerica because like gravity digital is like everywhere and yet
digital till divide
people know how to use their phone their laptop but they don't know how what's behind it and
for Terra Numerica it's very important to engage people and and and share with
them so they can be independent with digitals and what's going on in this in this a new world
so very often we hear that these are not my cup of tea and despite the very good quality of
qual of science mediation with high attendance at science fair open doors conferences
courses digital is not yet considered not as a part of our culture as art is
so therefore, we sorry I'm not very up, so therefore Terra Numerica wants to
disseminate the knowledge to the largest possible number of people,
and we aim at being a good vector for digital sciences in education and then bring equal opportunities for everybody boys and girls
also why Terra Numerica in our territory it's a very rich territory in interactions with
arts as you may know the south of France *alpha 19 bar* provence (name of a province?)
was, is still a very attractive place for artists so many came and stay and and produce in in the
area it's a very rich territory for art schools and like victorian studios as recently reopened
so cinema interactions lots of students and in society police and in nice and too long as well
a lot of research centers and private companies so very big nice area to to share and to to carry on
so the main goal of Terra Numerica was to bring together the whole digital sciences
actor which were on our territory and it was to not build well build something new but also
bring together all the people to make their experience and expertise in scientific meditation
their innovation creativity co-activities stronger also we very we're very keen in training
teachers professors and and sharing devices all devices around digital sciences
so Terra Numerica is a project still
it started we are now very I'm sorry sorry sorry sorry he lost my
we are now supported by our two funding members *cnrs India and universite cote d'azur*
we we have fully members from different areas like research and higher education laboratories
schools association private companies and local authorities as well our goal is to finally have
a big space to share and to show digital sciences but not only all the earn their interactivities
but also we are very keen on going in mainly in *interland* area because lots of secondary
schools high schools multimedia libraries don't always have access to those opportunities
we we have very open we are very open-minded and we've got like at the moment 150 people
working all together and including citizens students scientific administrative
staff artists everybody is is very welcome
so to give you a brief history of the project the project was born in into December 2018.
we were only four at the moment so in in 2 2019 we had to present and convince people and finally
we got a name and a logo which is Terra Numerica we got our first funding and first a key
achievement for Terra Numerica in 2020, then 2021 It was time for our, sorry our
research centers to sign an agreement and to encourage us to to carry on
so 2020 is 2022 is a big step for us because we are going to have a new pad as we said a very
big space 500 square meters where we are going to put down everything and it's going to be
able a place for sharing for researchers and people citizens to come and enter and
visit visitors and attend any kind of activities and the final goal for Terra Numerica in 2025
with the help of the local authorities is to open a dedicated place
to science meditation sorry meditation popularization of digital sciences and
we had the confirmation a few months ago so we are going to have like
5500 meters just for Terra Numerica, and just next to it, same place in Sophia Antipolis
5500 square meters for art and science linked to Terra Numerica and in connections
and after that the adventurers goes on we've got to carry on and work and produce and invent
and be different and attract more people so this is the place we we are going to
invest very soon where people are will be able to come and and visit and
it will be like the digital science fair all your all year round sorry and what we want is
to support innovative thinking inspire create share with everybody who's happy to come and
also we've got a little well not a little we would like to develop art and science in our project
and so just let open the windows on art and science and
as Picasso said everything you can imagine is real,
and this is what we are doing with Terra Numerica but not only
so we've got an agreement with Espace Art Concret de Mouans Sartoux and we are going to work
we are already working with them like Jean-Pierre as well showed you his project he's going to work
with with them as well and we would like to cross views between artists and scientists
so that could be a different level, like for instance the first example is Robert Delaunay
and you can as an artist, the creation and what an artist at INRIA can create
around the Delaunay Triangulations producing producing algorithm so that's an example
another example could be that that's a neural networks from another artist at INRIA,
and how your imagination could interpret neural networks in a different way
one of our scientists *Frederick Avi* who could not be there and *dorian mazurik* they both work
with this Espace Art Concret and for instance this is the work of Carl Andre which is a famous sculpturer,
American sculpture and it's the queens of, on the work of art,
and it's mixing arts, mathematics, and algorithm as you can see.
Also we've got heart is everywhere and there is another
project which is a spiral is in shape and it's an approach a multi-disciplinary approach and in this
case we want to erase awareness of observation reflection via the spiral as a mathematical
object or sharing with science and technology but not only like for instance the origami
origami to us could be a way to also introduce deep learning but very *vulgarated*
but deep learning as you repeat the same gesture to train and to make your origami become alive
so that could be you know lots of connections to explain science and the interconnections between
heart history of art and and whatever okay so we are
beginning to be a bigger project with a lot of ambitions and any contributions would be very very
welcome, we can share with you seminars creative and innovating project
and also from what we heard this morning new scientific research approaches
and it would be very important for us to carry on any kind of collaboration so
this is just a little video I hope it works and
huh
oops
so thank you very much to *harry gatou gozaimasu* we will we heard about your
summer school at the beginning and we would be very happy to maybe collaborate with you
also in next November in society police at *indriya* we're on organizing an *aca* tech with
young students and researchers and one of the major group research area would
be heart and sciences because we believe we can create and do lots of new things
and we we've got to in in the area we also hold the project *troisi ah* Koichiro Eto-san
you you've already heard about it so you could have a lot of interactions
around AI with a lot of scientists but not only twice a year Terra Numerica have
called for projects so we've got little finance to give the opportunity to artists or to scientists
to collaborate and to work together and being a non-artist and a non-scientific and living with
living and working with scientific and artists I believe that there is no that's it's not a
different word it's the same word sometimes as Jean-Pierre and some of you already said
the communication the the wording is not the same but the creativity and your sensitivity is just
the same always, I often hear mathematician say oh I'm so happy my algorithm is so beautiful
and it's in the same aspect that an artist could share his whatever production and also my final
sharing is next time we would be very honored to make a little video for Terra Numerica
or whatever and talk with now Tokui-sensei and maybe have his music
in back in the background to be more innovative thank you again (in Japanese) arigatou gozaimasu!
thank you very much for your presentation Magali-san then our presentation was
finished for session two so we'd like to start a discussion of of this session
then thank you thank you for all then I'd like to start a question to from myself
so why do you say can you hear me yeah I do yeah maybe you you have a limited time to so I'd like
to start question for you no no I i actually have plenty of time because if if it's
a quarter to ten two two up past 12 in France this is
one hour left I'm in Great Britain now so I have a lot of time not a lot but I have time
okay thank you I I'd like to ask you the many questions but at the first one point
how do you think the differences between the west and the east was for thinking about the
dystopia scenario for the future I i think that there is a how can I say increased by from the
fiction novel for example Frankenstein as you know a scientific science fiction novelist
Isaac Asimov named it as a syndrome of a Frankenstein so how do you think the
scenario is different for the west and the east oh the question of cultural relativity I heard that
well, we have the same I have, I'm jumping aside and I'm coming back to the discussion right
now. I'm also working on another *media-tech* and the cultural creator named the zombie and you
know there is huge discussion regarding if it's a production of the western imagination and if it
can also be rooted in the in non-western culture and civilization given that the relationship
in between the body culture the imagination of after after death and so on are quite different
from way on the way to another depending not only on culture but and I'm getting back
to the point on history you know that the the on not only culture but also history
for instance the the degree of historical trauma that you have for instance for walls
and the very specific relationship that you can have with technology and for instance you
Japan invented Godzilla and now this is the universal feature now the character that we
we can see everywhere but you invited it and and this now belongs to the global popular culture
and it can be recognized everywhere and so I think that there are framework for dystopian scenarios
similar on some aspects with a local variations regarding the very specific national history
let's say on the background of global history but but national histories for instance
and that's why there is a huge distribution of of this dystopian scenarios but if you
allow me just one more second I'm a bit talkative but just one second this dystopian
scenarios has also grounds for the acceptation of this for instance the fact that we all know
who is Frankenstein creator and we all accepted that we can create such let's say animals or
or human-like creatures regardless of the the outcomes and the fact that the creator can kill
the the create creator can kill the creator but you can fear a very specific scheme or object or
sign of symbol but accept it and dystopian can also be imaginary indeed
geological ideological facilitator for the acceptation of these things in my opinion
interesting I have this kind of a scientific fiction story
there are so many cultural background differences so maybe we can deepen this kind of stories
very much but I'd like to make broader to this topics so I'd like to ask you being
some how do you think the described stories from the east side and your presentation is
wonderful and also it's playful so I'm very interested in your story to a playful future
ah president can you can repeat the question again sorry I think the internet is not
evil in the you created the future scenario as a good site or a prayer site
I'm very interested in where did you come from this kind of attitude altitude you mean
the work I just created oh yeah okay well I think it's quite it's quite complicated because as
an artist I think any experience is going to our creation so I think my creation slightly
starts changing because I was moved back to China since 2020 and from then I think the whole
involvement and also the people how people are using the technology and the people's optimistic
altitudes on the technology in this whole environment is quite shocked me so so that that's
you can see that's my analyze of how what happens in these environments like from my slides
just in my presentation and so from that I was thinking compared to the study I would
compare to the the life experience when I was in London and I seen like quite different view
in China that everyone can so close engage with the technology that they bring the technology
fragments into their daily lives and then so in that case I think here everybody is artists
they are creating they're creating their how can I say they use their creation to
actually build the future day by day person by person and so when I seen this also I was raising
myself as an artist was the responsibility of being an artist in this technological arrow
so basically I'm more like critics on technology through my artworks and uh
and yeah that's that's that's experience again from from the from Beijing from China here
I'm not sure if I don't say it
yeah it's wonderful answer that everybody is an artist in China yeah
it's quite like you can't really you can't really feel which parts is the reality and
which part is fiction it's kind of all mixed up together the things you see in
it may next day appear in a daily life like in China you never know every day is a surprise
interesting thank you very much
for sang can you hear me magazine I have a question for you that how would you like to
make a place to collaborate with artists in your project can you hear me
nobody saying
he is not in a list of the names anymore wow
okay then
she came here again
if somebody have questions to speakers you can feel free to uh
on microphone then start to talk or please say something from chat
can you hear me
yes sorry *shiro* I lost you and I had to connect again ah okay so I'd like to I'll repeat the
question to you okay thank you I have a question is it any plan to make a collaborative
collaborative space in your project is there any future plan to collaborate with artists
oh yes indeed we we would like to to do that I mean Jean-Pierre is already an example
so far we have approached the Art Concret in Mouans Sartoux, but we would like to carry on and extend and
even outside the area the national I mean the France or elsewhere because like
we are going to have one 1 500 meters dedicated to art and science and it's very important to
to collaborate and to extend and so there are so many local artists as well it's a very rich
territory so yes we are very keen on on collaborating Koichiro with
you or any person who would like and also it is very important as you said
it's opening a new reflection on science aspects like with social environment
and with heart and the connections and I gather our project it's at uh
at a level just under your creativity
because for us the important is to share like we explain *AI* with a wooden
machine we've got lots of and it's to make people more confident and to show them that
digital a is everywhere but like art is everywhere as well to us so it's important that people trust
and feel more confident and it's like religion as Lionel,
I think it was Lionel (who) made (them) the relation,
I mean it's everyday you've got to convince people you've got,
and especially after what we've been through with the Covid you can all see that there is a lack of on
believing in science or in scientists so the problematics is everywhere and we've got to
carry on but yes we will be very happy to collaborate
I'm looking forward to collaborating with you yes we ideally we would we would have loved to welcome
you in March sometimes but because you are going back to Japan maybe next time with pleasure
Koichiro yeah thank you very much thank you so this is a time for discussion so is there any
questions between a speaker to a speaker we we are welcome to talk we have from you
i have one but meditate it will bring us very far okay I can try to jump here
since you work with the on the one side there is a close connection with artists and on the other
side you are working as in the heart of technology how do you get the issue of crafting
on the one side and creating on the other side all together
this is not an easy question this is a theoretical question I'm sorry for that but I know that there
are spaces right now in sciences where creation yeah you know crafting science is really inspired
by art and reciprocally so both of you are one of you how do you tackle this issue
well okay we have the main research area which is assistance for frail people
but at the same time we allowed us to wander
on other topics that are not really connected to our main research areas it happened in workshop
it happened in meeting well you know quite well that we have a lot of administrative meetings
and we try to make the best of them meaning that we have the opportunity to meet other
colleagues working in very different domains and what surprised me no doesn't surprise me but
what happened is that I see some kind of convergence in science as well meaning that
for example we have people trying to tackle numerical fluids problems and it just happens that
if you discuss with them during lunch you will see that they have
problems that are very similar to what problem you have and
you have developed algorithm for solving this problem they have developed their own algorithm
and it happens quite quickly frequently that well their tools may be quite useful
for us and reciprocally and in fact it's it's I will say it's just random
meeting so we just kiss with lawyers we discuss with biologists I have a biologist in my team
i will say just the open discussion
there is no systematic way to do it we have done a systematic approach at the beginning when we move
to industrial robotics to assistance robotics we spend two years making a lot of interviews with
customers help us medical community local authorities and really
it was very useful because we learned a lot of things we learned to avoid a lot of mistakes
which are very easy to make and I think that with artists it just happens that
it happens once a long time ago the world spread among the artists there is some team in
south of France which may help us to do whatever we want so this started accumulating and
the world spreads and that's it but there is no process for that in my opinion
thank you
sorry sorry so I was saying that in my first life at IRCAM when I was mostly working on
computer-assisted composition software tools we we had two kind of interactions between scientists
and artists in in the first situation the artist would come to the scientist with a problem
for instance a musical problem and would ask for help and expertise and algorithm and sometimes a
problem that was explained in a very lengthy way and seemed very complicated actually could
be solved with a very simple scientific or technological device or a simple algorithm
and sometimes a problem that seemed extremely simple to the artist and the artist thought that
he would really just need a little help to to achieve it
would actually become a huge scientific problem and maybe sometimes an unsolvable one
and this is very very interesting because it shows that the perception of complexity is very
different between artists and scientists scientists have issues of computability
which is a very difficult topic as as as you know and things that that are very obvious
in real life can become extremely difficult to model actually in in uh
a quantitative approach and sometimes the artists have a hard time understanding this because what
is simple for them and or complex and complicated for them it's totally different from what the
scientists would tackle as simple or complex so so we had this strange relationship in the
first place with the in the situation where the artist would come to the to the to the scientists
and asked so to speak for a service we had another kind of interaction which which went the other
way around so the scientists are also creative and creators except that they create scientific
theories or algorithms or models and they would come up with ideas of new models new algorithm
new fields and then they would talk about it because of course we have a lot of places to
talk workshops conferences seminars etc and then the artist would would come to the scientists and
say oh I never thought about that it's absolutely fascinating and it gives me an id for a new work
for a new piece maybe we can collaborate and so in this situation it it it would be it
would be the ideas coming from the scientist who would inform and influence the artist so that was
a traditional divide that was a traditional dichotomy between art and science as
a as a service-based relationship or art and science as a transfer or influence or transfer
of ids from one field to another it's two very different approaches and of course we we had
to cope with both but since I've been working on interactive and creative AI that is designing uh
kind of artificial create creatures that can live by themselves and interact on stage with musicians
now we're on in a very different situation because the the the concern now of the musician is how can
how can I have this artificial creature shut up for a moment because which is which is exactly
a question of control because we don't know really how to control them for instance we have
algorithm, AI algorithm, that generate music and do real-time machine learning in live situations etc
and they play music sometimes in a very smart way but they they they don't we see we still don't
have the cognitive model of intentionality and intrinsic motivation and all this that that makes
that that that can help us to decide when to start and when to stop doing something so generally
generally the the human who starts the computer and then the computer plays music it doesn't know
when to stop so so the the the human would would really like to have some more control over that
and so we so we are now moving to to to a paradigm of control and how to understand uh
control in the in the case where you have kind of artificial agents that that have a
that have a certain autonomy so the problem has totally shifted to to to this new issue of control
i think just what that
just one thing that I have to mention is that there is a parallel between in our collaboration
with that with a collaboration we have with doctors you have to be quite careful when you
do that for example if you go when you meet a doctor for the first time and tell him look you
have currently a medical process and I will teach you how to change it and to do it very efficiently
so you want to change everything then you are dead you have to learn to be incremental meaning
you have to simply state okay you have a process I will not change it I will just
help you on a given detail of this process to do it in a better way or to do it for you something
that you have currently doing we will avoid trying to do an example when you do a walking analysis
of a patient there is a classical test where you measure the time the guy takes to make 10 meter in
this straight line so so the surgeon is looking as at the chronometer
of looking at the way the guy is walking so the first thing we do is okay we will avoid you
looking at the chronometer because our machine will measure all the time for you
that's it they say okay because it was no big change for them and then we say well we can
measure also some of the things for example we have measured during this experiment this
particularity oh they say oh you can measure that so incrementally we add things we were able
to do since the very start of the program but we won't we don't want to say that at the beginning
and the doctors learned like the artists and when the request or the suggestion does not come from
us but from the doctors you have measured that but be possible to measure also that that we know we
have win and it's exactly the same process with artists in our first collaboration we were just
attacking with a small minor detail in the artwork showing it can be done and progressively
that you say oh you have been able to do that I would like to do another thing can you do it for
me and that's okay if you are these steps then you know that the collaboration will be quite fruitful
you have to be perfect
to fight your to fight your own mind we say okay we have this problem I know how
to deal with it completely and efficiently you have to learn that to be careful not do that
yes it is very smart approach and as you say the relation between artists
and scientists is a very delicate one and one has to treat it in a very delicate
yeah way you very much for
the cube okay and I think I we are almost running out of time for discussion so uh
no
okay okay I'd like to conclude this q a discussion session
and also this workshop so thank you very much for all participants
in this workshop you know for food for a discussion in this time so
can I across or who is a speaker for closing remarks yes I think you can you can conclude here
because I think Sebastian the chevalier *Jean Vivian* had to left earlier so you can conclude
okay I'd like to conclude this workshop and there was a wonderful presentation
so many wonderful presentations and there's so many issues to how to
deepen the relationship between art and advanced technology in this society
so I am very thankful to all the participants and for speakers and audience thank you very
much for making this workshop possible so I'd like to to end this workshop thank you very much
thanks a lot thank you thank you very much
thanks everyone thank you thanks take care bye bye thank you bye